# 大家好 最近十天半個月都在下雨 (註︰他這奇怪的句子已不是第一次出現)
Hi everyone! It has been raining for half a month in the previous ten days.
# 天天都在下雨 剛好今天出太陽啊
It rains every day. But just today, it's sunny.
# 河裡的那個水呀 都已經發水啦
The water in the river is, it's already overflowing.
# 就等於漲水了哇
I mean, the river is filled with water now.
# 好多魚在雨面
And there are a lot of fish in the water.
# 我買了一個這個
I've bought this one.
# 去山上
We go onto the hill,
# 搞一根竹子 把它做一個撈網出來
to get a bamboo. And then we can make a fishing net.
# 到時候
Then,
# 去河邊抓魚
we can go fishing on the riverside.
# 要上 要上山上砍一根竹子回來
I need to, I need to get a bamboo from the hill.
# 你看 今年長了好多竹笋啊
Look! There are a lot of bamboo shoots this year.
# 我把那竹子砍了時候差不多啦 (註︰我中文不好，不明白)
Last time I almost chopped all the bamboos.
# 現在又長那麼多出來
And now many are coming out again.
# 呃 到了那個秋天的時候就是一片
Eh, when, you know, the autumn comes, it will be,
# 又是一片
it will again be,
# 漂亮的竹林
a pretty bamboo forest.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個竹笋大吧
It's a huge bamboo shoot, isn't it?
# 夠大啊 這個
It's really huge.
# 那麼大 長大了就是那麼大的竹子
It's so big. It will be this big when it grows up into a bamboo.
# 很快的
It won't take long.
# 等於說 再過一個月半個月
It's like, after, after a month, or a fortnight,
# 一 再過半個月左右
a, after around a fortnight,
# 這又可以長到很高啦
it will be really tall.
# 這根竹子太丑啦
This bamboo is too ugly.
# 長歪啦
It's not really straight.
# 我回去 回去劈
I'll take it back, and break it there.
# 這裡沒有硬的東西
I can't find anything hard here.
# 要那個
I want some kind of,
# 硬的(是)[SIC]石頭
hard rock,
# 或者水泥之類
or something like concrete.
# 就好劈
It would be much easier.
# 不扎起來它是喜歡動
I need to tie it up here or it's always moving.
# 你看 這個圈子就出來啦
Look! A ring is formed.
# 你看 這個撈網做好啦
Look! The fishing net is done.
# 等明天我拿去
Let me give it a try tomorrow,
# 河邊試一下
on the riverside.
# 看一下效果怎麼樣
Let's see if it works well.
# 應該很不錯
It should be pretty good.
# 大魚小魚通通不放過
I'm not going to forgo any fish, neither big nor small,
# 連蝦米都可以撈得起來
not even the smallest shrimps.
# 昨天做的這個撈網 我來試一下
This is the fishing net that I made yesterday. Let me give it a try,
# 看撈不撈得到魚
and see if I can catch any fish.
# 一條都撈不到
Not even one.
# 哇 一個個 這兩隻
Wa! One by one, these two,
# 這兩隻鴨子哦
These two are ducks.
# 跑啦 不知道誰家的
They ran away. Whose ducks are they?
# 撈不到的 鴨子也撈不到
No, I couldn't catch anything, neither ducks,
# 魚也撈不到
nor fish.
# 幸好我帶了這個抽水機
Fortunately, my water pump is with me today.
# 開工開工
Let's start, let's start!
# 先把這個火打著
Let me start the engine first.
# 你看 這水都乾啦
Look! The water has been drained.
# 還有一點點水 放不乾的
There's still a tiny little bit of water. It can't be completely drained.
# 撈一下
So let me try.
# 哎喲 這裡有一條
Ayo! Here's one!
# 不是很大
It's not too big.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 刺人的
It stings!
# 這是鯰魚來的
It's a catfish.
# 你看
Look!
# 水深啊
It's so deep.
# 有竹子要不要
Do you want a bamboo?
# 踩著來
You can step on it.
# 拿來來
Yea, give me a bamboo.
# 這樣放嗎
Shall I drop it here?
# 嗯
Yup!
# 一條都沒有
Not even one.
# 那麼多小蝦米
There are so many small shrimps.
# 你看 這個滲水
Look! The water is seeping in.
# 抽都抽不乾的
There's no way to drain out all the water.
# 搞了半天
We've spent half a day draining out the water, look!
# 沒兩分鐘又滿啦
But now the pond is filled up again in just a couple of minutes.
# 鯰魚 你看
Catfish, look!
# 抓了一條鯰魚 你看
I've caught a catfish, look!
# 它大肚子的
It's pregnant.
# 把它放回去算啦
Let's just release it.
# 你自由啦
You're free now.
# 碰到我運氣好
Your luck brought you to me.
# 要不是看到你大肚子的份上
It's solely because of your pregnancy,
# 我就回去把你給煮啦
that I decided not to have you cooked.
# 誒 回去
Eh! Go home!
# 找你老媽
Reunion with you mom!
# 還有這石斑魚
And this is a freshwater grouper.
# 王斑魚看著太小啦
But it looks too small.
# 魚是小魚
Are all small fish.
# 算啦 算啦
Forget it, forget it.
# 把它放回去
Let me release them.
# 你看 這個是 這個是
Look! It's a, it's a...
# 這不知道甚麼魚 想鯇魚一樣的
No idea. I think it's something like a grass carp.
# 走吧 還有一條泥鰍
Go! And this is a loach.
# 泥鰍也放掉它去
Well, release it too.
# 全部放回去 全部放回去 不要啦
Release them, release them, all of them.
# 我看到幾條大魚在這裡
I saw a couple of big fish over there.
# 沒抓到
But I couldn't catch them.
# 滲水滲得太快啦
The water is seeping in too quickly.
# 好啦 回去啦
Alright! Let's go back.
# 不要啦
I give up.
# 下次我來釣
I'll come again with the fishing rod next time.